Guide to the Linda Butler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Linda Butler papers
1927-1980
YCAL MSS 10a
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.75
(3 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, writings, and a scrapbook concerning Margaret Marshall, the Marshall family, and Constance Mayfield Roarke.
Butler, Linda
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The material was donated by Linda Butler to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in June 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Linda Butler Papers consist of three boxes of correspondence and writings dating between the years 1927 and 1980.
The papers are divided into two sections, Correspondence and Writings. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Box 1, folders 12-30, contains letters from Butler's longtime friend, Margaret Marshall, spanning the years 1939-73. Marshall, literary editor for The Nation, discussed personal news, news of her family, and plans for the publication of manuscripts pertaining to their mutual friend, Constance Mayfield Rourke. There is also correspondence to Butler from Marshall's daughter, Judith Fleck, and her granddaughters, Anne Marshall Fleck and Catherine Lydia Fleck. These letters contain personal news as well as news of Marshall.
The collection contains several folders of letters to Linda Butler from author Constance Mayfield Rourke. The correspondence concerns personal news, information on her research projects, her travels, publications, and an art show which Rourke was arranging. Constance Davis Rourke, her mother, discusses with the activities of her daughter and her untimely death in 1941. There is also a folder of correspondence from Mildred Fore, Constance Davis Rourke's niece.
The Writings section is primarily composed of manuscripts by or about Constance Rourke. Included are biographical sketches of Rourke by Linda Butler, Nelle Curry, and Margaret Marshall, plus a copy of Rourke's eulogy by Reverend Charles W. Helsely. Writings by Rourke include an excerpt from Audubon and a photocopy of the printed version of Index of American Design. Also found in this section is a photocopy of the typescript of Marshall's autobiography, An American Memoir.
A scrapbook compiled by Butler concerning Constance Mayfield Rourke can be found in the Oversize section at the end of the collection.
Authors, American; Autobiography; Scrapbooks; Authors; Balph, Hellen; Butler, Linda; Fleet, Judith White, 1931-1971; Marshall, Margaret, 1900-1974; Roarke, Constance Mayfield, 1885-1941; Rourke, Constance Davis, 1846-1944; Marshall family
- Box and Folder List
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Balph, Helen, 1941-64 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Brooks, Gladys, 1962-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Butler, Linda, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Curry, Nelle, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fleck, Anne Marshall, 1972-74 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fleck, Catherine Lydia, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Fleck, Fred, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fleck, Judith, 1958-71 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fore, Alice, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fore, Mildred, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Marshall, Margaret, 1939-73, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12-30)
    - Rourke, Constance Davis, 1927-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31-37)
    - Rourke, Constance Mayfield, 1928-39 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
    - Rourke, Constance Mayfield, 1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Rubin, Joanie, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Ryan, Mrs. John Austin, 1976-77 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - WRITINGS
    - Butler, Linda
      - Constance Rourke
        - Notes: holograph and typescript (Box 2, Folder 47)
        - Introduction, photographs, bibliography: typescript, carbon, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 48)
        - Typescript, carbon, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Clippings, 1964-76 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Scrapbook
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Oversize, Box 3, folder 62
    - Curry, Nelle
      - The Constance Rourkes: typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Helsley, Reverend Charles W.
      - For Constance Rourke: typescript, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Marshall, Margaret
      - An American Memoir: typescript, photocopy, annotated, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53-56)
      - Constance Rourke: typescript, photocopy, annotated, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Constance Rourke: Artist and Citizen: printed version, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Rourke, Constance
      - An American Memoir: typescript, photocopy, annotated, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Audubon: excerpt, typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Index of American Design: printed version, photocopy (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - OVERSIZE
    - Scrapbook, 1928-56 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 62)